Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Series 4: Return of the French Army from Virgina to Boston, July - December, 1782, dates not examined; more than 48 packets
  - 108. Plans des différents camps occupés par l'Armée aux ordres de M. Le comte de Rochambeau, undated; more than 46 packets 46 pp 32 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39)
    - 139. Camp à Bullion's Tavern, le 9 Septembre, 13 miles de Sommerset-Court-house, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-32)
      MS, No. 39-32. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 184]
      Cf. the map, "Points of Interest, Liberty Corner," in Historical Booklet of Bernards Township, N.J., published to commemorate the Bicentennial, 1760-1960 (Basking Ridge, N.J., 1960), pp. [62-63].
    - 140. Camp à Pompton-Meeting-house, le 12 Septembre, 15 miles de Wippany, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-33/34)
      Thirty-fourth Camp at Pompton Meetinghouse [Pompton Plains]. Also "Camp à Wippany, le 10 Septembre, 16 miles de Bulllion's Tavern. Voyès la Campagne 1781, 21e camp. (Le 11 Séjour)" [no map]. 12-13 September 1782. Fifteen miles from the previous camp at Whippany, where each of the two brigades had remained an extra day. No new map of the Whippany camp was included in this series, since the camp was in the same position in 1781; see No. 66.
      There had also been a camp at Pompton Plains the previous year (No. 65), but since the present camp is in a slightly different position, there is a new map. Comparison of the two maps and reference to the "Metting-house," shown on both, indicate that the greater part of the troops camped this time on the eastern side of the main road. In both instances, as indicated by the points on the symbols for regiments, the camp "faces" the enemy, who occupied Manhattan and Staten Islands to the eastward. This 1782 map includes a larger area than the earlier one, extending northward to the bridges across the river at the top of the sheet. (The two branches of the Pompton are called the Pequannock and Wanaque on modern maps.) An advance unit is shown here near the river crossing, where a small work protecting a strategic point in the road communication system is situated. The road branching off to the left (labeled upside down) went to Ringwood and thence, via The Clove, to New Windsor, which is on the Hudson above West Point. The road here designated as "Chemin de Suffrantz" sent to present Pompton Lakes (Passaic County), then through the Ramapo Valley (present U.S. Route 202) to Suffern, New York, the next camp. This route is shown on map, No. 50, and is described in Itinerary 3.
      MS, No. 39-33/34. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 184-185]
    - 141. Camp à Suffrantz [Suffern], le 13 Septembre, 15 miles de Pompton-Meeting-house, undated; 1 item (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-35)
      Thirty-fifth Camp at Suffern [in New York]. 13-14 September 1782. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Pompton Plains. The stream is the Ramapo River. The previous year's camp at Suffern is shown above on the map, No. 64, which appears reversed in relation to the present one, it being the cartographer's practice to orient his map with the direction of the march at the top of the sheet.
      MS, No. 39-35. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 185]
    - 142. Camp à Hawer-Straw, le 14 Septembre, 15 miles 1/2 de Suffrantz. Le 15 & 16 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-36)
      Thirty-sixth Camp at Haverstraw. 14-16 September 1782. Fifteen and a half miles from the preceding camp at Suffern. The First Brigade remained here for three days, the Second Brigade for two, before crossing the Hudson at King's Ferry on 17 September. The First Brigade camped on this site already used the previous year (cf. No. 63) north of Cedar Pond Brook, in what is now the village of stony Point. The Second Brigade camped farther south, along the road leading from the village of Haverstraw to "Smith-house." This was the house of Joshua Hett Smith, later known as "Treason House," where Arnold and Andre spent the night of 21-22 September 1780; the site is now occupied by the New York State Rehabilitation Hospital (West Haverstraw). The stream at the far right of the map is Minisceongo Creek.
      MS, No. 39-36. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 185]
    - 143. Camp à Peak's Kill, le 17 Septembre, 9 miles 1/2 de Hawer Straw. Séjour jusqu'au 23 September, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-37)
      Thirty-seventh Camp at Peekskill. 17-23 September 1782. Nine and a half miles from the preceding camp at Haverstraw. The entire army is shown in camp here (Lauzun's Legion, at right, nearest the Hudson) on hillocks to the south of the village of Peekskill. The site is in the southern part of the now-populated part of Peekskill. The small stream at top of map (south) is Dickey Brook; the single peak beyond it, Blue Mountain. For its relationship to the larger general area, see maps of the 1781 campaign, Nos. 48 and 62. On the way to its camp here at Peekskill the French army had crossed the Hudson at King's Ferry (Stony Point to Verplanck's Point) and then marched past the American camp, which was closer to the ferry landing. The French halted at Peekskill for a week before proceeding on 24 September, eastward and farther inland, to their next camp at Hunt's Tavern (also referred to as the Crompond encampment).
      MS, No. 39-37. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 185-186]
      According to a "Plan du Camp de Pisk-kill" in Cromot Dubourg's "Atlas," No. 8 (Service Historique de la Marine, Fonds du Service Hydrographique, MS No. 2847), Washington's army had occupied a position on these same heights in "1780" (presumably an error for 1781).
      Accounts of the stop at Peekskill, including the review by General Washington, are in the journals of Clermont-Crèvecœur (pp. 78-79) and of Verger (pp. 165-167).
    - 145. Camp à Huntz Tavern, le 24 September, 8 mles de Peak's Kill. Séjour jusqu'au 21 October, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-38)
      Thirty-eighth Camp at Hunt's Tavern. 24 September - 21 October 1782. Eight miles from the preceding camp at Peekskill. The army had already camped here the previous year, as shown on map, No. 61. The road running from the bottom to the top of the sheet (shouth) is Crompond Road, present State Route 35 (U.S. 202) in the town of Yorktown, New York. The lower or the two roads leading into it from the right is present Baldwin Road. Hunt's Tavern (not so labeled on this map) is the house situated at this junction. The road leading off at this point to the left (which the army would eventually take when resuming its march to Salem Center) is present Hallock's Mill Road. An outlet of Crom Pond (the larger of the two "Etangs") curves around the high ground where part of the army camped behind the tavern and then crosses Hallock's Mill Road. The "Qier Gal" (Quartier General), i.e., Rochambeau's Headquarters, was situated here in Samuel Delevan's house. For the story of Delevan's claims against the General, see Verger's journal, n. 158. The position of the "Hunt's Tavern camp" within the general "Crompond" area is shown on the next map.
      MS, No. 39-38. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. Another, less accurate version of this map appears in Cromot Dubourg's "Atlas," No. 9 (Service Historique de la Marine, Fonds du Service Hydrgraphique, MS No. 2847), where it is entitled "Plan de Crompond Occupé par l'Armée Française depuis le 24. 7bre. Jusqu'au 22. 8bre 1782." In the lower left corner there is a vignette representing truncated and cracked columns, perhaps intended to symbolize the breaking up of the allied army. [Rice/Brown, p. 185]
    - 147. Camp à Salem, le 22 Octobre, 13 miles de Huntz Tavern, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-39)
      Thirty-ninth Camp at Salem [Salem Center, Westchester County, New York]. 22-23 October 1782. Thirteen and a half miles from the Hunt's tavern (Crompond) camp. The route from Hunt's Tavern via Hait's (or Haight's) Tavern (Somers) and Dean's Bridge (Purdys), to Salem is described (in reverse) in the 1781 "Itinerary from Providence to the Campe at Philipsburg." This portion of the route had not, however, been taken in 1781, because of the change in itinerary; see note to map, No. 24. Thus the army marched over this road for the first time in 1782. From here to Providence, Rhode Island, the march was by brigades: the Bourbonnais Brigade (including the Bourbonnaid and Royal Deux-Ponts regiments) a day ahead of the Soissonnais Brigade (including the Soissonnais and Saintonge regiments).
      The locality here designated as "Salem" is now known as Salem Center, which is in the town of North Salem, Westchester County, New York, near the Connecticut line. The stream at the right of the map is the TIticus River (its enlargement into the Titicus Reservoir now begins at approximately the point shown at the bottom of the map). The road running parallel to the river is present State Route 116. The two roads branching off to the right and leading to Bedford corrsepond roughly to present Turk Hill Road and June Road.
      The building on the left-hand side of the road in the center of the map (to the right of the letters "em" in Salem") is the manor house built ca. 1773 by the Loyalist Stephen Delancey. During the Revolution it was confiscated by the patriots and used as a courthouse and jail. From 1790 to 1884 it was occupied by the North Salem Academy and since that time has been the Town Hall for the town of North Salem..
      MS, No. 39-39. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 188]
      Regarding Delancey's house see Fred C. Warner, "Famous Landmark Restored, Restoration of North Salem's Town Hall," The Westchester Historian (Westchester County Historical Society), XXXXIV, No. 1 (Jan.-March 1958), 10-12
    - 148. Camp à Dambury, le 23 Octobre, 11 miles de Salem, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-40)
      Fortieth Camp at Danbury [in Connecticut]. 23-24 October 1782. Eleven miles from the preceding camp at Salem Center, New York. When marching to Danbury the army passed through Ridgbury where it had camped the previous year (cf. No. 37); henceforth it followed, in the opposite direction, the route already taken in 1781. The road from Ridgebury to Danbury is shown on map, No. 23.
      The road at the lower right coming in from the previous camp at Salem is present West Wooster Street, which joins Main Street at right angles. The "Meeting house" shown at this point is the Congregational Church, no longer standing; its site was near the present County Courthouse. The route went right to the foot of Main Street, then left into South Street. The second "Meeting house" shown here is the early Episcopal Church, which has also disappeared from this site. A bit farther along, a road (approximately present Coal Pit Hill Road) branches right (south) to Stratford and Newtown. Beyond this junction, on high ground to the north of the road, two regiments camped. The artillery was farther forward near the bank of the Simpaug, a small tributary of the Still River. After crossing the brook the route (corresponding to present Shelter Rock Road) led on towards Newtown, as shown on map, No. 23.
      The "hôpital" in the lower part of the map was a military hospital maintained by the Americans, which local tradition places in the "Hoyt House" on present Park Avenue.
      MS, No. 39-40. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 188-189]
    - 149. Camp à Farmington, le 28 Octobre, 13 miles de Barn's Tavern, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-41/44)
      Forty-fourth Camp at Farmington. Also "Camp à New-Town, le 24 Octobre, 12 miles de Dambury; Voyés Campagne 1781, 10e Camp. (le 25 Séjour)" [no map], "Camp à Break-Neck, le 26 Octobre, 15 miles de New-Town. Voyés Campagne 1781, 9e Camp" [no map], "Camp à Barn's Tavern, le 27 Octobre, 13 Miles de Break-Neck. Voyès campagne 1781. 8e Camp" [no map]. 28-29 October 1782. Thirteen miles from the preceding camp at Barnes's Tavern (in Marion). On the march from Danbury to Farmington the army had camped at Newtown (41st camp, 24-26 October 1782), Break Neck (42nd camp, 26-27 October), and Barnes's Tavern (43rd camp, 27-28 October), but no new maps are included in the present series since the positions were the same as those occupied on the 1781 southward march. Cf. Nos. 36, 35, and 34. The route is shown on Nos. 23, 22, 21, and 20.
      The army had camped in Farmington the previous year during its southward march, but the campsite had then been south of the village, as shown on No. 33. The 1782 camp was in a different location, more in the village, as shown on the present map. The brook, when proceeding north along Main Street, is a road leading west, corresponding to present Meadow Road. The camp of the infantry regiments would thus have been roughly along the line of present Garden Street; the artillery and wagons camped east of Main Street along Hatter's Lane.
      The general street plan of Farmington, as shown here, has changed little over the years. Many of these houses still stand. The building enclosed in a small square in the upper part of the map is the Congregational Church, built in 1772-1773 by Judah Woodruff.
      MS, No. 39-41/44. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 189]
    - 151. Camp à East-Hartford, le 29 Octobre, 12 miles et 1/2 de Farmington. Séjour jusqu'au 4 Novembre, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-45)
      Forty-fifth Camp at East Hartford. 29 October - 5 November 1782. Twelve and a half miles from the preceding camp at Farmington. Owing to the extra séjour, or halt, the entire army was encamped here together, as shown, from 30 October through 4 November. The camp was east of the village and of the Hockanum River, on either side of the road to Bolton Center. When the army stopped here the previous year, only one regiment (Soissonnais) camped in this position. The other regiments had been west of the village closer to the banks of the Connecticut in an area not included on the present map; cf. No. 32.
      It was here at East Hartford that Rochambeau announced that the army would march to Boston and embark there for the West Indies. Many had hitherto supposed that they would remain in winter quarters at Hartford; cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, p. 81. See also Von Closen, pp. 263-264, and Chastellux (4), II, 477.
      Dr. Ezra Stiles, journeying westward with his wife, met up with the French army at this time. He noted in his diary (4 November) that he saw the First Division at Bolton (where General Rochambeau visited him at the Reverend Mr. Colton's house), and then, on 5 November, when proceeding from Bolton to East Hartford: "Met & passed the 2d. Div. of French Army, probably 1500 men. The whole sd. to be 4000, I judge 3000. We stopt our chaise near half an hour in passing the Troops, & afterwards above half an hour in passing 2 Divisions of Wagons, I judge 200. Some of them sd. they had 500 Waggons for whole Army... ."
      MS, No. 39-45. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 190]
      Dr. Ezra Stiles' account taken from The Literary Diary of Ezra Stiles, ed. Franklin B. Dexter (New York, 1901), III, 45.
    - 152. Camp à 2 miles audelà de Bolton Meeting-house, le 4 Novembre, 14 miles d'East-hartford, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-46)
      Forty-sixth Camp, Two Miles beyond Bolton Meetinghouse. 4-5 November 1782. Fourteen miles from the preceding camp at East Hartford. In June 1781 the army had camped hear Bolton Meetinghouse (present Bolton Center), as shown on Nos. 17 and 31. This time the camp was 2 miles beyond the meetinghouse (i.e., southeastward) in a position that appears to be near the Hop River and one of its small tributaries. This would be in the southwestern corner of the present town of Coventry, or northwestern corner of the present town of Andover (incorporated separately in 1848), along present U.S. Route 6.
      MS, No. 39-46. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 190-191]
    - 153. Camp à Windham, le 5 Novembre, 16 1/2 miles de Bolton, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-47)
      Forty-seventh Camp at Windham. 5-7 November 1782. Sixteen and a half miles from Bolton. There was an additional day's stop here. The camp was east of the village on either side of the road leading to Canterbury (present State Route 14). The previous year the army had camped west of the village on the banks of the Shetucket; cf. Nos. 16 and 30.
      No artillery units are shown on the map. Von Closen (p. 263) notes that the artillery obtained permission to march as far as Providence one day in advance of the First Brigade. See also Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, p. 81.
      MS, No. 39-47. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 191]
    - 154. Camp à Cantorberry, le 7 Novembre, 10 miles de Windham, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-48)
      Forty-eighth Camp at Canterbury. 7-8 November 1782. Ten miles from the preceding camp at Windham. The stream at the bottom of the map is the Little River. The campsite is on high ground south of the road (present State Route 14) before reaching "Westminster Meeting," the building shown to the left of a small triangular bulge in the road. The rebuilt eighteenth-century church still stands on this spot. The "Meeting-house" shown at the top of the map in the village of Canterbury proper is on the site of the present Congregational Church (built in 1805). Although the army had passed along this route in June 1781, it did not then camp at Canterbury; cf. No. 16.
      MS, No. 39-48. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 191]
    - 155. Camp à Walen-Town, le 8 Novembre, 10 miles de Cantorberry, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-49)
      Forty-ninth Camp at Voluntown [Sterling Hill, Connecticut]. 8-9 November 1782. Ten miles from the preceding camp at Canterbury. "Walen-Town," I.e., Voluntown, here refers to the present village of Sterling Hill in the town of Sterling, Windham County, Connecticut, and not to the present village of Voluntown in the town of that name, New London County, some nine miles to the south. In 1782 the town of Voluntown included territory that was later, in 1794, incorporated separately as the town of Sterling.
      The army had passed through Vountown but had not camped there in June 1781, as shown on the road map, No. 15. Dorrance's Tavern (still standing) is the building just above the letter "w" in "Town." General Chastellux in his Travels recorded much information about the tavern-keeper, Samuel Dorrance, and his family; see Chastellux (4), Index. The army's 1782 camp was in the fields east of the tavern on the north side of the road (present State Route 14-A).
      MS, No. 39-49. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 191]
    - 156. Camp à Providence sur le chemin de Boston, le 13 Novembre, 4 miles de l'ancien Camp, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-50/52)
      Fifty-second Camp at Providence. Also "Camp à Waterman's Tavern, le 9 Novembre, 10 miles de Walen-Town. Voyés Campagne 1781, 2e Camp" [no map], "Camp à Providence, le 10 Novembre, 15 miles de Waterman's Tavern, l'armée sur deux Lignes dans l'ancien Camp de la Brigade de Soissonnois. Voyés la Campagne 1781, 1er Camp" [no map]. 13 November - 4 December 1782. Proceeding from Voluntown (Sterling Hill) the army made its next (50th) camp at Waterman's Tavern on the site occupied the previous year (cf. Nos. 14 and 28) and then, upon reaching Providence, camped again (51st camp) on the western outskirts of the town, as it had done in June 1781 when beginning the march to the Hudson (cf. Nos. 14 and 27).
      After pausing for three days on the former camp ground the two brigades marched through Providence to another site north of town, as shown on the present map. According to Von Closen (p. 267), the move was determined by the landowner's refusal to agree to the cutting of wood on his property. The new camp, described my Verger as "barracks in a wood" (p. 169), was on the farm of Jeremiah Dexter, overlooking the Boston road, in what was then North Providence. Present Camp Street and Rochambeau Avenue are in the vicinity.
      The troops remained here in North Providence until Vaudreuil's ships at Boston were ready to receive them. They left successively in four divisions: Bourbonnais on I December, Soissonnais on the 2nd, Saintonge of the 3rd, and Royal Deux-Ponts on the 4th. The artillery, however, had left Providence for Boston a fortnight earlier (16-17 November), "because of the large amount of materiel to be embarked" (cf. Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, p. 81).
      The inclusion of a stretch of the "Pattukey River" (i.e., the Pawtucket, now called the Seekonk), upper right of th map, is a reminder that a French vessel, the Fantasque, was anchored here. As noted by Verger (p. 169), a detachment commanded by M. d'Espeyron, major of the Soissonnais Regiment, comprising one company from each of the four regiments, was embarked on the Fantasque, also used as a hospital ship. This vessel, which was in bad repair, did not join Vaudreuil's fleet as planned and remained here until early February 1783. Thus French soldiers were to be seen in Providence for another two months after the departure of the main corps of the army.
      It was at Providence that General Rochambeau took leave of his army and handed over the command to Baron de Vioménil.
      MS, No. 39-50/52. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 192]
      An account of the "French Encampment in North Providence" in Stone, French Allies, pp. 309-327, includes a map of the vestiges of the camp and huts as platted in 1865. Further documents from the state and town records, including Dexter's claims for damages and thier settlement, are printed in Howard W. Preston, Rochambeau and the French Troops in Providence (Providence, 1924), pp. 18-23. See also Forbes and Cadman, I, 167-174.
    - 157. Camp à Wrentham, Le 1er décembre, 16 miles du camp de Providence, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-53)
      Fifty-third Camp at Wrentham [in Massachusetts]. 1-4 December 1782. Sixteen miles from the preceding camp at North Providence. The camp ground lay between Lake Archer (the "Etang" at the left of the map) and Main Street, near present State Route 1-A, the old road from Providence to Boston.
      MS, No. 39-53. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 192-193]
    - 158. Camp à Dedam, Le 2 décembre, 16 miles de Wrentham, undated; 1 item 33 x 29 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-54/55)
      Fifty-fourth Camp at Dedham. 2-5 December 1782. Sixteen miles from the preceding camp at Wrentham. The road from Wrentham coming in at the lower left of the map crosses a small stream (Lowder Brook) before joining another road, which in turn leads to the "Meeting House" (Congregational Church) on Dedham Common. The river at the top of the map is the Charles. The camp was southeast of present St. Paul's Church on ground lying between present Court, School, Washington, Worthington, and Richards Streets.